There's a nutrient that not only slashes
your liver fat, confirmed across several
randomized control trials, but also
protects your liver from becoming
overwhelmed and overburdened. Now, I'm
going to start implementing it in my own
diet because I'm incredibly impressed
with the results, and I think that you
will be, too. But here's the kicker.
While it helps everyone, it helps some
people even more than normal. Let's get
into the science, the nuances, and my
personal new approach to
resistant starches. And actually on that
last one, I may need your help, but
we'll get to it. First, the nutrient
resistant starches. There are many
excellent quality placeboc controlled
randomized control trials published in
extremely high-profile journals like
Cell Metabolism and Nature Metabolism
that all point the same direction.
Resistant starches are an amazing class
of molecules. In fact, in more ways than
what we're about to go over here, which
is why I have more analyses coming out
on the topic. But let's stick to the
subject at hand, visceral fat and liver
health. The reality is I ran across this
first study because I ran across a video
by Dr. Jill Carvalo. And after doing a
bit of my own digging, I uncovered even
more evidence. Six studies in fact. The
thing is when people maintain their
nutrition but they supplement with
resistant starches they do experience
elimination of visceral fat that
specific body fat that surrounds and
infiltrates into our organs. Now
visceral fat is quite harmful and having
lots of it exposes us to premature
death. That's about as simply as I can
state it. Look for yourself. This is
visceral fat. The blue line is the group
supplementing with resistant starches
and the reddish line is the placebo
group not given any resistant starches.
Now we have the before measurements and
the measurements four months later. We
want the lines to go down and sure
enough they do for the supplementing
group. In fact, the difference is an
over 300% increased elimination of
visceral fat compared to the placebo or
in absolute terms nearly 20% more. No
matter how you slice it, this one group
of molecules has a great effect which is
shared through other visuals. Like here,
the images on the left are before and
the images on the right are after. These
are MRI images of body fat. The more
red, the more visceral fat. Now, I don't
know about you, but the right side
certainly looks like it has less. A
perfect illustration. The point being,
across multiple studies, resistant
starch supplementation dramatically
slashes harmful visceral fat in our
body. Here's the thing, though. The fat
around our organs is critically
important to reduce. But there are other
types of fat aside from the vein
attempts to be Achilles that are also
critical to excellent health. And they
tend to go hand in hand. I'm talking
about intrahypatic fat. the fat not
around the organs but inside the cells
themselves in this case your liver. This
manifests as an abundance of lipid
droplets otherwise stated as fat
droplets stuck inside the liver cells.
Now having too much of these lipid
droplets in the liver cells leads to
liver cell dysfunction. Considering that
your liver is made up of liver cells
that means that your liver isn't too
happy with you. So when we look at the
levels of these fats in our liver cells
here, we're measuring the intrahypatic
triglyceride content, which is a
scientist impressive term for liver fat
found inside the cells. Clearly, we want
that to go down. And what do you see?
That's right. The blue line, the
resistance starch supplemented group
experienced significant reductions,
about six times more liver fat
eliminated compared to the placebo. And
this ends up being reflected in other
measures as well, like liver
inflammation and liver damage markers
are also reduced. This all yields a
conclusion that resistant starches not
only punch visceral fat in the gut, but
they also have a massive effect in
reducing liver fat previously stuck
inside the liver. You're now beginning
to understand why I'm so keen to add
this to my life, and maybe you'd be
interested, too. I'll get into all that
soon. But I'm also always extremely
interested in understanding why this
happens. Keep in mind, resistant
starches are never absorbed, hence their
name, resistant, like a toddler not
wanting to do something. Resistant
starches kick and scream. Figuratively,
of course, the idea of being absorbed
into the bloodstream. So, if it stays in
our intestinal tract, um, exactly how is
it presenting such profound benefits?
Well, like other fibers, resistant
starches may not be absorbed into our
bloodstream, but they do interact with
our microbiome, the vast population of
microbes living in our large intestine.
So, researchers take poop samples from
people not fed resistant starches, the
placebo group, and poop samples from
those exposed to resistant starches, and
then implant them into mice. This is a
direct way to test if resistant starches
are having a positive effect on liver
health and visceral fat through our
microbiome or something else is going
on. The research indicates that
resistant starches do enable their
benefits through the microbiome which
ultimately translates to our improved
liver health. Now that we have a focus,
we can then try to triangulate the
specific microbes bacteria that are
creating this healthful or harmful
relationship. ultimately may be
identified that a particular bacterium
is abundant when our microbiome is not
exposed to resistant starches. Now, I
want to pause here because this is
important as you can reflect right now
and ask yourself if you eat a lot of
green bananas, cooled potatoes, cooled
pasta, lentils, chickpeas, and the like.
If the answer is no, then you probably
have some exposure to these bacterium in
your gut. So, what does that mean for
you? Well, check it out. We're looking
at liver fat levels again with mice
exposed to the bacterium while the
bacteria are still alive in the middle.
And when they're dead, but still present
in the far right. Clearly, in both
conditions, there's some increased liver
fat, at least in the living scenario.
So, this means that A, the bacterium is
harmful to liver health, including other
measures that I'm not going to show you,
and B, consuming too little resistant
starches, like those foods that I
mentioned, may offer a disadvantage as
your gut may contain this harmful
bacterium. Now, I want to be more clear
here. We would need more data to be
certain, but this is the direction of
the data is pointed. In addition, while
these foods that I mentioned earlier do
offer some resistant starches, many of
these foods are still quite low in the
absolute sense. So, it would take a
dedicated effort to really consume
sizable amounts. At any rate, we have
pretty good data that consuming
resistant starches changes our
microbiome for the better, likely
reducing the amount of certain harmful
bacteria that directly contribute to
fatty liver. But here's the thing.
There's another layer to this because
while most people likely benefit from
resistance starch consumption, there's
some people that experience even greater
benefits. And we actually see that
distinction here. We're looking at our
trusty fat found inside of our liver
cells again. And the left, the pinkish
red boxes are the one group of people
and the blue are another group of
people. Clearly, one group experiences
significant reductions in liver fat
while the other experiences minimal
improvements. The reason is that while
both groups are exposed to resistant
starches, one group is considered a low
responder while another is called a high
responder. This is again believed to be
because of differences in the
microbiome. Certain microbes almost
certainly bully beneficial microbes out,
thereby overpop populating with less
useful microbes that don't take
advantage of the consumed resistant
starches. All right, regardless of your
resistant starch response status,
there's profound benefits to be had from
supplementation. So, let's discuss how I
plan on using this information and you
could consider doing something similar.
Before I discuss that and ask for your
help, I'll be getting into how to
determine if you're a high or low
responder to resistant starches and even
the relationship between the amino acid
veene and fatty liver and more in my
full analysis, my extended video of the
one that you're currently watching. It's
included as a physionic insider along
with an accompanying article, monthly
podcasts, live sessions with me, and
much more as you can see here. Now, if
you're interested in full access to all
my work, short summaries, and all, then
check out the Physionic Insiders. It's
linked in the description. Now, I'm not
great at making things taste all that
appetizing, and resistant starches are
generally consumed in powdered form,
specifically as high amalos maze or
green banana powder or potato starch,
doesn't dissolve well, and heating it is
a no-go. So, I'm considering adding it
to some shake of some sort. If you have
suggestions, I'm all ears. Now, I'll
keep my eyes open in the comments. That
said, the amount consistently used
across studies showing remarkable
effects of resistant starch is around 40
g. That's a lot. Could less also be
effective? Definitely, but we don't have
enough data on that. So, 40 grams is the
current best target. Now, I'll be
supplying some good sources as I do with
all my supplements that I review in my
master supplement guide, also included
as an insider if you want more help.
Now, it might be best considering that
it can lead to gastrointestinal
discomfort if you go from 0 to 40 too
quickly. So, to start low, maybe five
grams per day for a week and then up it
to 10 grams and so on. Now, aside from
palletability,
I'm excited to add this to my routine,
especially considering significant other
health benefits that I'll be covering in
the near future. So, stay tuned for
that. Speaking of which, there's other
science on eliminating visceral fat and
improving liver health that I've covered
before. Check it out right here. Thanks
for tuning in. I hope this that this was
informative. And again, if you have
recommendations for what to mix in with
the resistance starches, then let me
know in the comments. I appreciate it.
See you.